Guide to the Andover Newton Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Individuals A-L, Series I
  - Hall, Robert Beals
    - "Jottings of a Lifetime" - 4 bound volumes of notes, 1863-1869 (Box 70, Folder 1-2)
    - Membership records, Wolfesboro, NH Congregational Church, 1873-1875 (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Memorabilia, including photos, obituaries, 1870-1876 (Box 70, Folder 4)
  - Handspicker, Meredith
    Meredith Brook "Jerry" Handspicker was born June 25, 1932, in Malden, MA. After attending Bates College and Yale Divinity School, he was ordained into United Church of Christ in 1957. In 1961 he was appointed to the faculty at Andover Newton Theological School where he served as professor of theology until 1999. He died on February 28, 2016.
    - Correspondence related to teaching at Andover Newton Theological School, 1969-1988 (Box 67, Folder 1-2)
    - Writings and documents related to theological education, including D.Min program at Andover Newton Theological School, 1991, no date (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and documents related ecumenical work, Commission of Faith and Order of World Council of Churches, 1963-1966 (Box 67, Folder 4-5)
    - Miscellaneous unpublished writings and notes, No date (Box 67, Folder 6)
    - Memorabilia re. death of Handspicker's wife Diane, 1996 (Box 67, Folder 7)
  - Hazelton, Roger
    Hazelton (1909-1988) taught at Andover Newton Theological School from 1945 to 1957 and from 1965 to 1978, appointed Abbot Professor of Christian Theology in 1951. He also taught at Pomona College and was dean of the graduate school of theology at Oberlin College 1960-1965.
    - Personal scrapbook containing photographs, clippings, articles, programs and other memorabilia (Box 44)
    - Bound volume of letters and tributes presented to Hazelton at the time of his departure from Andover Newton Theological School, 1957 (Box 44)
  - Hopkins, Samuel
    Hopkins was born September 17, 1721 in Waterbury, CT. He graduated from Yale College in 1741. Ordained in 1743, he served at First Congregational Church, Great Barrington, MA (1743-1769) and First Church, Newport, RI (1770-1803). He died in Newport on December 20, 1803.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Available on microfilm - Positive #130
    - Diary covering July 15, 1754 to November 13, 1756, 1754-1756 (Box 62, Folder 1)
      After 11/13/1756 date there are 6 pages in shorthand; at end of diary there are 2 pages of marriage records
    - Memorandum book, 1790-1800 (Box 62, Folder 2)
      In addition to dated entries regarding financial accounts, there is a key to shorthand system used by Hopkins.
    - Correspondence, including Hopkins to Joseph Bellamy, Sarah Osborn, Susanna Anthony, Stephen West, and John Ryland., 1763-1801, no date (Box 62, Folder 3-9)
      Full listing of correspondence available in Box 62 Folder 3
    - Essay: "A dialogue between Philenicos and Crito upon the atonement", No date (Box 62, Folder 10)
    - Essay: "A paraphrase with notes and practical observations upon the epistles of Paul to the Galatians and Ephesians", No date (Box 62, Folder 11)
    - Sermon notes, including "Fragment: Question. What is meant when it is said (1 John 3:9) "Whatsoever is born of God doth not commit sin?"; Biblical text in shorthand; Psalm 84: 10, 1757, 1802, no date (Box 62, Folder 12)
    - Article on the slave trade published in Newport Mercury (May 1, 1784) (Box 62, Folder 13)
    - 4 items of unknown provenance, including letter fragments, journal entries, letter of Moses Hopkins to George C. Sibley/July 7, 1834, and letter of John Ferguson which includes statement by Caleb Tenney regarding accuracy of Ferguson's memoir of Samuel Hopkins/Dec 11, 1843 (Box 62, Folder 14)
  - Horr, George Edwin
    Horr (1856-1927) graduated from Brown University in 1876, spent one year at Union Theological Seminary, and then attended Newton Theological Institution, graduating in 1879. He was ordained as a Baptist minister and served churches in Tarrytown and Charlestown, MA. He was editor-in-chief of The Watchman from 1891 until 1903 when he was appointed chair of the History of Modern Christianity at NTI in 1903. Horr served as President of the Newton Theological Institution from 1908 to 1925.
    - Thesis: "Translation and Critique on Lessing's 'Die Erzichung des Menschengeschlechts'" by Richard J. Inke and George E. Horr, 1915 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Papers submitted to Prof. Horr by Newton Theological Institution students on various aspects of church history: by E. N. Armstrong, F. M. Davis, Shozo Hashimoto, Margaret S. Holley, Herbert C. Long, No date (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Papers submitted to Prof. Horr by Newton Theological Institution students on various aspects of church history: Teizo Tada, George Everett Tomkinson, Theodore Wehle, anonymous, 1920, no date (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Hovey, Augusta
    Augusta Rice Hovey was the wife of Alvah Hovey (1820-1903) who taught at Newton Theological Institution in Newton Centre, Massachusetts from 1849 to 1903 and was President of the Institution from 1868-1898. Mrs. Hovey was active in Baptist and philanthropic work. See Record Group 288 for the papers of Alvah Hovey.
    - Dated correspondence, 1848-1905 (Box 64, Folder 1-16)
    - Undated correspondence: arranged by correspondent, A - T, No date (Box 64, Folder 17-21)
    - Letters received after death of Mrs. Hovey's husband, 1903 (Box 65, Folder 1-2)
    - Letters and notebook related to Mrs. Hovey's work with Newton Hospital, 1885-1900 (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Letters related to Mrs. Hovey's work with Boston (New England) Baptist Hospital, 1896-1900 (Box 65, Folder 4-7)
    - Correspondence and documents related to Mrs. Hovey's husband, Alvah Hovey, 1886-1889 (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous family documents, including relating to Marshall Rice, Noah Hovey and "W.H.", 1849-1855, no date (Box 65, Folder 9)
  - Hovey, George Rice
    Hovey (1860-1943) was the son of Alvah and Augusta Hovey. He graduated from Brown University in 1882 and after teaching at Yale became professor of Hebrew at the Richmond Theological Seminary in 1887. He was later president of Wayland Seminary and College in Washington, D.C. and professor of Theology and Philosophy and president of Virginia Union University.
    - Letters to Hovey, including from Alvah Hovey, Frederick L. Anderson, Charles Rufus Brown, 1881-1907 (Box 65, Folder 10-14)
  - Ives, Hilda Libby
    Ives was the first woman ordained in Maine, in 1926. She ministered small rural parishes and taught at Andover Newton Theological School.
    - Subject file of collected articles and pamphlets primarily relating to agricultural missions, consumer cooperatives, parish credit unions, rural churches and ministry, arranged alphabetically by author of publication, 1930s - 1940s (Box 66, Folder 1-24)
  - Judson, Adoniram
    Adoniram Judson was born in Malden, Massachusetts, August 8, 1788. He graduated from Brown University in 1807 and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1810. While at Andover, he became a member of a student group, The Brethren, which was organized to encourage interest in the foreign missions movement. He was a leader of the group of students who petitioned the General Association of Massachusetts for financial support in missionary work, a move which later resulted in the formation of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. In 1811 he was appointed one of the first five missionaries sent from the United States. He married Ann Hasseltine, February 5, 1812, and the following day was ordained at Tabernacle Church in Salem. Later that month Adoniram and Ann left for India with Samuel and Harriet Newell. During the voyage Judson studied the question of baptism. After further study of the issue in India, the Judsons became convinced of the validity of the Baptist tenet of believer baptism; and both Adoniram and Ann were baptized by English missionaries. After months of frustration in dealing with authorities of the East India Company and after a brief layover in the Isle of France, the Judsons finally arrived in Burma in 1813 under the sponsorship of Baptists in the United States. Judson's entire missionary service was in Burma. In addition to published works on baptism and the missionary cause, Judson is well known for a translation of the Bible into the Burmese language and publication of an English-Burmese dictionary. The Burmese -English portion of the dictionary was unfinished at the time of his death, and was completed by Edward A. Stevens, a missionary colleague. In April, 1850, Judson died during a sea voyage.
    - Correspondence of Adoniram Judson
      - From Robert Ralston, George Thom; to Samuel Nott; to "Dear brother", 1811 (Box 71, Folder 1)
      - Journal letter written June-July 1812 regarding Judson's trip to India, which tells of life on the ship, initial impressions of the people in Bengal, updates on Baptist missionaries, and the British government's attitude toward missionaries (18 pages) (Box 71, Folder 2)
      - From Darius Griswold, 1812 (Box 71, Folder 3)
      - To Mary Ann May, Sister Stevens, Mary C. Beecher, Sarah Havens, 1837-1846 (Box 71, Folder 4)
      - To Edward A. Stevens, Mrs. Stevens, Heman Lincoln and family, Gardner Colby, A. Gillette, 1847-1849 (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence of family members and others
      - A. Judson [Sr.] to General Goodwin, 1809 (Box 71, Folder 6)
      - Ann H. Judson to Mrs. Carleton, Mrs. Baldwin, 1820, 1822 (Box 71, Folder 6)
      - Elnathan Judson to Mrs. Carleton, 1823 (Box 71, Folder 6)
      - Emily Judson from Gardiner Spring, Heman Lincoln, I.T. Fields, Francis Wayland, Edward Bright, Jr.; to Mrs. Stevens, to unidentified, 1851-1854, no date (Box 71, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous collected letters, including from William Carey to "Dear Bro" (no date); Harriet Newell to Mrs. Carleton (1812); from G. R. Bliss to John H. Raymond describing Judson (1845); Isaac Colburn to family members, 1812 - circa 1875 (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - Manuscript items
      - Remarks of Judson before American and Foreign Bible Society, No date (Box 71, Folder 9)
      - Items related to Burmese language and Burmese-English dictionary, including leaf from manuscript dictionary, "A Grammar of the Burmese language", booklet of grammatical notes, 1822, no date (Box 71, Folder 10)
      - Burmese - English dictionary manuscript (2 volumes), 1852 (Box 71, Folder 11-12)
      - Burmese - English dictionary manuscript edited by Edward A. Stevens (742 numbered pages; some pages missing), 1852 (Box 72, Folder 1-6)
    - Memorabilia
      - Images of Adoniram Judson (Box 73, Folder 1)
      - Images and biographical information about Ann Hasseltine Judson and Emily C. Judson (Box 73, Folder 2)
      - Images of Salem ordination of first missionaries, Judson's birthplace, scenes in Burma (Box 73, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous memorabilia, including lock of Judson's hair, Centennial medal and publicity, 1840-1913, no date (Box 73, Folder 4)
  - Kimball, James
    Kimball was born in Fitchburg, Massachusetts, on November 21, 1789, being the ninth in a family of fourteen children of Deacon Ephraim and Betty (White) Kimball. He graduated from Yale College in 1816. He entered Andover Theological Seminary but was expelled due to a disagreement with his professors in the his Senior year (1818-1819). Kimball died in Fitchburg, on January 24, 1821.
    - Documents related to Kimball's dismissal from the seminary, 1818-1821, no date (Box 68, Folder 1-6)
    - Letters from Kimball's sister Elvira Kimball, primarily to seminary faculty re. her brother's health, 1820 (Box 68, Folder 7)
    - Lecture or sermon notes (Box 68, Folder 8-10)
    - Broadside: "Catalogue of Professors and Students of the Theological Seminary, Andover, Mass. - February, 1820" (Box 68, Folder 11)
    - November 28, 1812 issue of Columbian Centinel, newspaper published in Boston (Box 68, Folder 12)
  - King, Henry Melville
    King was born September 3, 1838 in Oxford, Maine. He graduated from Bowdoin College and Newton Theological Institution and was ordained on August 28, 1862. He served as an Assistant Instructor of Hebrew at NTI from 1859 to 1863. He served the Dudley Street Baptist Church, Boston from 1863 to 1881, Emmanuel Baptist Church, Albany, NY from 1882 to 1891, and First Baptist Church, Providence, RI from 1891 to 1906. He was an author during his retirement from 1906 until his death on June 16, 1919 in Providence.
    The collection is comprised of 18 scrapbooks which include the following: King publications, reviews of King publications, letters from individuals responding to publications and reviews, and articles on subjects of interest to King. The subject scrapbooks focus on Baptist history in Rhode Island and Massachusetts, history of First Baptist Church of Providence, and the following general categories: devotional, temperance, illustrations, social questions, the Bible, missions, doctrinal issues, and poems and hymns.
    - Scrapbook volumes 1, 2, 3: miscellaneous articles, articles by and about HMK (Box 77)
    - Scrapbook volumes 4, 5: articles by HMK, reviews of books and articles by HMK; letters received about books and articles by HMK (Box 78)
      Correspondents are listed individually in the original finding aid for the collection available at the repository.
    - Scrapbook volumes 6, 7: reviews of books and,articles by HMK; letters received about them (Box 79)
    - Scrapbook volume 8: articles on the First Baptist Church, Providence, R.I. and early Baptist history in Massachusetts and Rhode Island. some articles by HMK (Box 80)
    - Scrapbook volumes 9, 10: articles on Baptist history in Massachusetts and Rhode Island, and First Baptist Church, Providence R.I., many articles by HMK with letters in response (Box 81)
    - Scrapbook volumes 11 (Devotional articles), 12 (Articles re. temperance), 13 (Illustrations), 14 (Social Questions) (Box 82)
    - Scrapbook volumes 15 (The Bible), 16 (Missions), 17 (Doctrinal issues), 18 (Poems and hymns) (Box 83)
  - Labaree, Benjamin Woods
    Labaree was born on June 5, 1865. He attended Hartford Theological Seminary and was a missionary in Persia (now Iran), from 1894 until his death in March, 1904. Labaree and his parents, Benjamin and Elizabeth, served in Persia under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions.
    - Scrapbook of clippings - poems and articles, 1898 (Box 89, Folder 1)
  - Lamson, William
    Lamson was born in Danversport, MA on February 22, 1812. He graduated from Colby College in 1835 and attended Newton Theological Institution from 1839 to 1841. He was ordained in 1837 and served Baptist churches in Gloucester, MA (1837-1839,1842-1848), Thomaston, ME (1840-1842), Portsmouth, NH 1848-1859, and Brookline, MA (1859-1875). He died in Gloucester on November 29, 1882.
    - Sermons, 1866-1871, no date (Box 90, Folder 1-10)
  - Leverett, Warren and Washington
    The Leveretts were twin brothers born December 9, 1805 in Brookline, MA. They both graduated from Brown University in 1832 and enrolled at Newton Theological Institution. Washington graduated from NTI in 1836, having taken brief leaves to teach a Columbian College and Brown University. He taught at Shurtleff College in Illinois from 1836 until 1868. While on leave from NTI for health reasons, Warren worked as an agent for the American Bible Society and as an elementary school teacher. He returned to NTI in 1836 but discontinued his theological studies after completing 2 1/2 years of the 3 year course of study. Leverett served as a professor at Shurtleff College in Illinois from 1839 to 1868. He died on November 8, 1872 and Washington died on December 13, 1889. More detailed biographical information is available in the first folder of the collection.
    - Four notebooks, primarily notes from courses taken at the Newton Theological Institution, 1833-1835 (Box 91, Folder 1-4)
      Three notebooks are attributed to Warren and one to Washington. Faculty lectures represented are: Henry Jones Ripley, Professor of Biblical Literature, James Davis Knowles, Professor of Pastoral Duties, and Irah Chase, Professor of Biblical Theology. The lecture notes provide the earliest documentation of Newton curriculum in the Andover Newton collection. For a more detailed description of the contents of the notebooks see an inventory in the first folder of the collection.
  - Lindsay, Samuel Macaulay
    Lindsay graduated from the Newton Theological Institution in 1913. He served Baptist churches in Brooklyn, NY and Brookline, MA.
    - Seven bound volumes of typescript notes and sermons, including volumes titled "Life of Christ", "I Am the Door", "Religion and Life", No date (Box 92)
    - Six bound volumes of typescript notes and sermons, including volumes titled "Christ in Art", "The Men of the Bible", No date (Box 93)
    - Eight bound volumes of typescript notes and sermons, including volumes titled "The Three Dimensions", "The Song of Spring", No date (Box 94)
  - Loesch, Russell and Mary
    Russell Talcott Loesch was born December 30, 1907 in Garrettsville, Ohio. After graduation from Oberlin College in 1932 and Andover Theological Seminary in 1935, he served Congregational churches in Massachusetts, Florida, and New Jersey from 1936 to 1942 and 1946 to 1975. During World War II he was a chaplain in the U.S. Army Air Corps. From 1955 to 1961 he served as Minister to Chaplains and Armed Forces Personnel of the Congregational Christian Churches and United Church of Christ. He died on January 12, 1989.
    Mary(Polly)Francis Loesch was born July 7, 1910 in Andover, MA and married Russell in 1937. She died on June 7, 1981.
    For more detailed biographical information see the first folder of the collection.
    - Letters from Mary (Polly) to Russell, written during his chaplaincy service in World War II, 1943 October - 1944 August (Box 95, Folder 1-11)
    - Letters from Mary (Polly) to Russell, 1944 September - 1945 June (Box 96, Folder 1-10)
    - Letters from Mary (Polly) to Russell, 1945 July - September, no date (Box 97, Folder 1-3)
    - Letters from Russell to Mary (Polly) during his chaplaincy service, 1940 June - 1944 August (Box 97, Folder 4-19)
    - Letters from Russell to Mary (Polly), 1944 September - 1945 October (Box 98, Folder 1-14)
    - Letters from others to Russell, 1943-1944 (Box 98, Folder 15)
    - Memorabilia, including photos, diary entries from 1929, and obituary for Russell; essay, "My Parents and World War II," by Robert K. Loesch; newspaper clippings; "Orange Tails: The story of the 358th Fighter Group and Ancillary Units", 1943-1991 (Box 98, Folder 16)
    - Memorabilia and biographical documentation related to Russell and Mary (Polly) Loesch (Box 167, Folder 1-2)
    - Documentation related to Loeschs' trips abroad, including circular letters, journals, itineraries, 1957-1977 (Box 167, Folder 3)
- Individuals M-Z, Series II
  - Marshall, Harry I. and Emma
    Harry Ignatius Marshall (1878-1952) graduated from Dartmouth College, Ohio State University, and the Newton Theological Institution (1903). He and his wife Emma served as missionaries in Burma under the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society and wrote extensively about the Karen People of Burma.
    - Family correspondence: primarily from Emma Marshall to her sister Anna Smith, written while the Marshalls were in Burma. Letters provide detailed descriptions of their mission work., 1928-1934 (Box 99, Folder 1-2)
    - Family correspondence: from the Marshalls to their children, who were staying with family members in the U.S., 1930-1933 (Box 99, Folder 3)
    - Circular letters from Marshalls while in Burma, 1932 (Box 99, Folder 4)
    - General correspondence of Harry Marshall, 1929-1934 (Box 99, Folder 5)
    - General correspondence of Emma Marshall, 1931-1933 (Box 99, Folder 6)
    - General correspondence of Anna Smith (Emma's sister), 1931, no date (Box 99, Folder 7)
    - Circular letters of other Burma and India missionaries, 1931-1933 (Box 99, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and documents related to Karen Theological Seminary, Insein, Burma, 1927-1931, no date (Box 99, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence and documents related to seminary students' evangelistic trips and campaigns, 1927-1931 (Box 99, Folder 10-12)
    - Notes of Harry Marshall, 1931-1932, no date (Box 99, Folder 13-15)
    - Collected material, including newspaper clippings, articles, essays, reports, 1930-1934, no date (Box 99, Folder 16-18)
    - Documents in Burmese script (Box 99, Folder 19)
    - Memorabilia, 1931-1934, no date (Box 99, Folder 20)
  - Millard, William Harold
    Millard was born January 18, 1877, in Waltham, MA. He graduated from Harvard in 1899 and from Newton Theological Institution in 1902. In October 1902 Millard and his wife Edith sailed for China under sponsorship of the American Baptist Missionary Union.
    From November 1902 until March 1908 Millard taught at Wayland Academy in Hangchow (Hangzhou). In 1907 he served as acting principal there. In April 1908 he was transferred to the Theological Seminary of Shanghai College as Professor of New Testament and Theology. He died there on March 9, 1909, from complications related to diabetes.
    - Letters from Millard primarily to his parents, describing his missionary work in Hangchow, 1902-1907 (Box 100, Folder 1-8)
      The letters are typescript transcriptions of originals and are arranged as though the compiler intended to publish the collection. Location of originals is not known.
    - Letters from Millard, written primarily to his parents, from Shanghai, 1908-1909 (Box 100, Folder 9)
    - Extracts of letters from Millard to his fiancee Edith Adams, 1902 (Box 100, Folder 10)
    - "Words from a few of those to whom he was best friend," typescript testimonials regarding Millard, with authors including Percival R. Bakeman, J. C. Robins, Dr. Eubank, Mr. Latimer, Professor Tong, A.F. Ufford, Arthur Rugh, circa 1909 (Box 100, Folder 11)
    - Typescript writing regarding geography of Hangchow, No date (Box 100, Folder 12)
  - Millett, Joshua
    Millett was born in Leeds, Maine on January 26, 1803. He graduated from the Newton Theological Institution in 1835 and was ordained as a Baptist minister in 1836. He served churches in Charlestown, Cherryfield, and Wayne, ME. He died on March 10, 1848.
    - Lecture notes taken by Millett at Newton Theological Institution: courses by Professors Chase, Knowles, and Ripley, 1833, no date (Box 101, Folder 1-3)
    - Sermons, arranged by scriptural text (Box 101, Folder 4-13)
    - Miscellaneous manuscript writings, 1832, no date (Box 101, Folder 14)
  - Mitchell, Hinckley Gilbert
    Mitchell was born on Feb. 22, 1846, in Lee, NY. He was educated at Wesleyan University, Boston University School of Theology, and Leipzig University. He was a Methodist minister and taught at Wesleyan, Boston University School of Theology and at Tufts University from 1910 until his death in 1922. Mitchell was Secretary of the Society of Biblical Literature and Exegesis and editor of its Journal from 1882 to 1888.
    - Letters written to Mitchell in connection with his role as Secretary of the Society of Biblical Literature and Exegesis and editor of its Journal, 1883-1889 (Box 102, Folder 1-16)
    - Letters to Frederic Gardiner, Mitchell's predecessor as editor of Society of the Biblical Literature Journal, including from George Edward Day, 1881-1882 (Box 102, Folder 17)
  - Morrow, Honoré Willsie
    Morrow (1880-1940) was a novelist and magazine editor. Her novel Splendor of God, published in 1929, is a fictionalized account of the missionary work of Adoniram Judson and his wife Ann in Burma [now Myanmar] during the late 1800s.
    - Handwritten manuscript and notes for Splendor of God novel, 1929 (Box 103, Folder 1-4)